[Music]
Hello everyone, I am Dr. Vikas Singhal, Senior
Consultant, Department of
Surgery, Medanta Hospital, Gurgaon. Today
we will discuss whether the
problem of hernia can come
back despite the operation. So, can hernia
recur after surgery for hernia? So, the
short answer to this is about
five to 10% recurrence risk of
hernia. Hernia can come back despite the operation. There are
many reasons for this.
Generally, the success rate of our hernia surgery is
around
92.5%. This means that if we
repair the hernia of 10 patients, the
hernia of one of them can come back. The
reason for this is that
sometimes the hernia is very big, very
complicated, or the factors of the patient, the
tissues of the patient are
very weak. Therefore, whenever
we perform hernia surgery, we have to do a
very detailed evaluation.
Normally, many times the patients who come to us have been
operated on somewhere else before.
Many times they have undergone two or three
hernia operations
and they come to us when the
hernia has returned for the third time and we have to do hernia
surgery for them for the third or fourth time also because there is no other
treatment to fix a hernia
apart from hernia
surgery. Just like the tissue gets torn, similarly
when the muscles of our wall get
torn, one way to repair them is by
stitching them and
supporting them. In the same way,
in a hernia operation, we repair the hernia
and support it with a mesh or a gash. This is our priority. In fact, our
hernia recurrence risk is extremely low and in the
region for this, there is a lot
of planning done in the surgery and
we normally do a CT scan of the patient to
see why the hernia has returned
or if we are doing hernia surgery for the first time
and it is a big hernia, then we have to do a
lot of research.  The operation has to be done with planning.
Sometimes we
optimize or prepare the patients for the surgery before the operation
so that their surgery is done
in the best conditions so that the
success rate of their surgery is as
high as possible.
Sometimes there are some factors like if there are
heavy smokers, we stop them from smoking. If they
stop smoking for a few weeks, then
actually the risk of complications
reduces. Their coughing gets reduced,
such that there is no constant coughing
pressure. After the hernia repair operation, the
second thing is that if some patients are
very overweight or obese, they suffer
from obesity, we help them that
if the hernia surgery is
not an emergency, then they should first lose weight so that
they get the best result after the operation, there are
minimum complications
and the risk of hernia coming back is minimized. So
yes, the answer is that hernia can come back in
spite of surgery in about five to 10%
but the  The good news is that if you go
with a lot of preparation, this risk of
hernia coming back can be
minimized and can sometimes
try to make it less than 5%, but with them, you need a lot
of cooperation from your
patients. There should be a thorough
evaluation, your patients should be following up with
us. They should not take major action today. Cutting
down smoking, eating a good high
protein diet, reducing weight, managing
obesity, so there are a number of things you can do to
reduce this risk of hernia coming back
and see hope that more than 90% of
over 60 patients will have a successful outcome from
their hernia surgery. Thank you.
[Music]